Citizens Party (U.S.) Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Citizen Party (U.S.) Records 1976-1993 (bulk 1979-1981)
MSS85427
Citizens Party (U.S.)
2,800 items
8 containers
3.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Political party composed of environmentalist and liberal groups. Correspondence, meeting notes, local chapter records, financial records, membership directories, newsletters, newspaper clippings, and printed matter pertaining to the organization of the Citizens Party, the formation of its platform, and its early campaign efforts.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Commoner, Barry, 1917-2012.; Harris, LaDonna.; Leahy, Dan (Daniel B.)
Organizations
Citizens Party (U.S.)
Subjects
Environmentalism--United States.; Liberalism--United States.; Political parties--United States.; Presidents--United States--Election--1980.
Places
United States--Politics and government--1945-1989.
Provenance
The records of the Citizens Party (U.S.) were given to the Library of Congress by Dan Lieberman in 2008. Additional records were given by Dan Leahy in 2018.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the papers of Barry Commoner.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the Citizens Party (U.S.) are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Organizational History
Date Event
1979 Established in Washington D.C. as a progressive, environmentalist, and liberal political party Registered with the Federal Elections Commission
1980 Held first national convention in Cleveland, Ohio, where delegates nominated Barry Commoner for President and LaDonna Harris for Vice President
1981 Terry Bouricius is first party candidate to win an election when elected to the Board of Aldermen in Burlington, Vt.
1984 Held second national convention in St. Paul, Minn., where delegates nominated Sonia Johnson for president and Richard Walton for vice president
1987 Disbanded after low votes cast for party nominees in 1986 elections
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Citizens Party span the years 1976 to 1993, with the bulk of the material ranging in date between 1979 and 1981. The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or material type, with a significant portion concentrated in a grouping representing papers maintained by Dan Leahy, executive director, national secretary, and executive committee member of the party from 1979 to 1981.
The collection primarily chronicles the Citizens Party’s organization at the national and local level, the formation of its platform, and its campaign efforts, especially during the 1980 presidential election. Very little material related to the party’s activities beyond 1983 and ultimate disbandment in 1987 is represented in these records. Material types include correspondence, Executive Committee and Steering Committee meeting notes, campaign strategy files, local chapter procedures and records, financial records, membership directories, newsletters, newspaper clippings, and printed matter.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
Container List
- Campaign material, 1980-1981, 1993 (Box 1)
- Conventions, 1980-1982 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1980-1983, 1992, (4 folders) (Box 1)
- Dan Leahy papers (Box 1)
  - April convention, 1980, (3 folders); (1 folder) (Box 1, Box 2)
  - Atlanta, Ga. chapter, 1980-1981, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Ballot access, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Chronological file, 1979-1980, (3 folders); (5 folders) (Box 2, Box 3)
  - Commoner, Barry and LaDonna Harris campaign, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Context papers, 1976-1979, (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - Executive Committee, 1980-1981, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Financial documents, 1979-1980, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Fundraising, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Inter-party relations, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Local chapter recognition, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Local organization, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - National office, Washington, D.C., 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Newsletters and clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
  - Nominations, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Platform, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Political Action Committee, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Position papers, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Seattle, Wa. chapter, 1980 (Box 6)
  - State caucus procedures, 1980, (3 folders); (2 folders) (Box 6, Box 7)
  - Steering Committee, 1979-1980, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Strategies, 1979-1980 (Box 7)
  - Western Regional Coordinating Committee, 1980 (Box 7)
- Executive Committee and officers, undated (Box 7)
- Financial records, 1980-1983 (Box 7)
- Meetings, 1980-1981 (Box 7)
- Membership, 1980-1981, (1 folder) (Box 7, Box 8)
- Notes, 1980-1981 (Box 8)
- Organization (Box 8)
  - Local chapters, 1979-1981 (Box 8)
  - National, 1981 (Box 8)
- Publicity (Box 8)
  - Brochures and circulars, 1979-1982 (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1979-1983, (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Newsletters, 1980-1982 (Box 8)
- Speeches and statements, 1980-1981 (Box 8)